<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Hamid Gadirov</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu_645fa481986063ef.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stable Diffusion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/scikit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/scikit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stable Diffusion is a deep learning model for generating images from text prompts, and in this project, I implemented it as a fun experiment to explore its capabilities and customization.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optical Flow</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/pytorch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/pytorch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project explores optical flow, a technique for estimating motion between two frames in a video sequence. Optical flow is widely used in video processing, motion tracking, and computational photography.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ML for Visualization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/project/pandas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/project/pandas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project explores how &lt;strong&gt;autoencoders&lt;/strong&gt; can improve the visualization of &lt;strong&gt;spatial ensembles&lt;/strong&gt; by extracting meaningful features before applying dimensionality reduction techniques like &lt;strong&gt;UMAP&lt;/strong&gt;. The goal is to create more expressive 2D projections that effectively capture spatial structures and spatio-temporal behaviors in ensemble data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-contributions&#34;&gt;Key Contributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluating Autoencoder Variants&lt;/strong&gt;: We assess how different &lt;strong&gt;architectures and parameter settings&lt;/strong&gt; affect the quality of visualizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feature Extraction for Projections&lt;/strong&gt;: Autoencoders significantly enhance UMAP projections, improving how ensemble structures are represented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Guided Selection of Autoencoders&lt;/strong&gt;: We propose a method to select the best autoencoder configuration based on &lt;strong&gt;projection metrics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficient Labeling Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;: Instead of labeling the entire dataset, we show that a small subset of labeled ensemble members is enough for selecting an effective autoencoder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;applications&#34;&gt;Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project applies this approach to two different ensemble datasets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geological Data&lt;/strong&gt;: Channel structures in soil generated using &lt;strong&gt;Markov chain Monte Carlo simulations&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fluid Dynamics&lt;/strong&gt;: Time-dependent experimental data on &lt;strong&gt;droplet-film interaction&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By leveraging &lt;strong&gt;machine learning&lt;/strong&gt;, this project provides an automated, data-driven approach to improving visualization in ensemble analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details and implementation, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/HamidGadirov/ML-for-EnsembleVis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
